so I wrote up a response that I'm not
going to read it just because you can
read it it's on my website but I will
just kind of extrapolate a little bit
some of the key points I made there I
want to suggest that I take two stances
here the weak argument is that integral
should at least become more informed
about what capitalism is and that we
have actually a completely kind of under
interrogated under theorized conception
of capitalism and the forms of
capitalism that we talked about integral
capitalism yada yada it mostly ignores
the entire tradition of heterodox
economics and so I think once we have a
more comprehensive view of the nature of
the capitalist economy then I get to my
stronger argument which is that when you
understand the dynamics of capitalism it
becomes clear that if you stick to the
principles of integral theory and of
integral meta theories more broadly and
especially people like bats car then we
should be if we're committed to our own
principles at the very least
post-capitalist and potentially actually
anti-capitalist and so when people say
the anti-capitalist movement is a green
meme phenomena to me they're using green
meme and two terms like second tier as
substitutions for actual thought right
we need to actually think through what's
going on in these movements and spend
time dialoging with them in their most
sophisticated forms and not using
developmental theory as a way
essentially to dismiss them and not
listen to them so i'm going to say the
strong argument is the one that i'm
going to propose a day just because this
is a polarized debate so of course to
think about how capitalism works more
deeply we need to get into a bunch of
complex theories in economics including
the nature of money they need to a value
theory right I'm not going to get into
that today but we can but I think what i
want to say here is that the principles
of interval theory talk often about
transcending and including but i think
there's a basic confusion in there
between enduring and transitional
structures all right so that's one issue
here so you can think about transcending
capitalism but negating and preserving
it as opposed to transcending button
in its entirety so that's I think one of
the sticking points here is we think as
developmentalist we need to always
transcendent include and to be integral
you can't be anti anything but in fact
to be integral your auntie a lot and we
need to admit that you know I'm anti
injustice right I don't transcendence
include injustice I get rid of injustice
right so the idea that there's this
inclusiveness that includes everything
becomes a problem and so I love integral
theory because of the inclusiveness but
we need to become more articulate about
what it means to be opposed to things
and to speak you know and to take power
and to use force occasionally when
necessary to be opposed to things and
not to find ways to rationalize and
justify them right so I think there's an
underlying issue here about strategy
versus compromise right and I'm not
going to get into that but hopefully
we'll have a chance to get into that but
it's key to think about here the
conscious capitalism movement and what
that means and the degree to which that
is a compromise or strategy right so to
preempt my kind of Integrative comments
I would say something along the lines of
conscious capitalism should be seen as a
gateway drug to an actually
post-capitalist form of intoxication
social intoxication so to that extent
i'm not opposed to conscious capitalism
but i am opposed to a form of conscious
capitalism that sees no alternative to
capitalism right and that's exactly what
they I'm gonna use that term
occasionally the man that's what they
want you to think that there is no
alternative that somehow capitalism act
is actually a naturally occurring thing
that markets are like nag nature and you
watch David Attenborough and David
Attenborough says in the BBC nature
programs that the flower is
entrepreneurial and exploits the be to
have it and what you see is that we're
actually so ingrained in our ideology
that we read backwards into nature and
posit the social system we saw and when
Darwin came with the theory of evolution
it was Charlie Sanders pursue said this
is nothing but the gospel of greed right
so we naturalize capitalism and we can't
see be
did and it's a failure of imagination
there's also worth saying that
capitalism is by its nature and I'm
using this term and I haven't to find it
but one of the things that defines it by
my definition is that it cannot imagine
its own eternity which is to say that
it's a form of social organization that
runs up against limits inevitably the
greatest example is the pursuit of
endless profit especially compounding
rates of profit and if you know anything
about compounding rates of growth they
are radically unsustainable on a limited
playing field right and so as soon as
you say well capitalism isn't about the
endless pursuit of profit that I'm
saying you're talking about something
else and not capitalism right now that's
fine we can have that debate but the way
catalyst is structured and what it means
to cater to corporate interests is to
help those corporations turn a profit
and then you get into value theory and
you think where does excess money come
from where does surplus value come from
it comes from the exploitation of labor
primarily and we can debate that but I
will stick pretty closely to that so the
reason we don't have robot robot
factories because you don't make money
through technological innovation in the
long run because everyone can build that
you make money by having access to
exploitable labor and this is the main
reason that we have corporations of
global scope that can push nation-states
around and it's primarily so that we can
find ways to exploit labor but there's
only so long that there are peasant
populations that can be brought into the
urbanized industrial system and made
into the wage laborers that they've
become there's only so much peasant
labor that we can eventually include
into the system which means that that's
another limit to capitalist growth is
that eventually we will be able to will
have to stop exploiting people profits
rates will decline right the last thing
I'll say is that there's an intrinsic
relationship between markets and
violence and the idea that a market is a
naturally occurring phenomenon has never
existed in history and if you look at
the history of markets what you see is
that wherever there's a market there's
somebody with a gun or stick right so
the nature of the relationship between
capitalism and violence cannot be
ignored and the escalation of violence
in a global scale has
everything to do with the nature of the
capitalist kind of reorganization that
began in the wake of 1972 and the
neoliberal counter-revolution